What if TRT stops working? Someone said,
"I'm around thousand nanogs per diliter,
I guess, and still feel exhausted every
day."
Um, so I'd say I want to know how you're
getting that blood result. So, I need to
know what your regime is, how compliant
you are with it. Are you really being
compliant? Um, then um and then when you
got the blood test, what your free
testosterone is. So, rather than going
around the houses, I'll talk about it
sequentially. So um you want to know
total testosterone that's very good
thousand I think in English units that's
probably around about the 30 mark upper
end of reference range something like
that. So that's that's a good number. So
what what are you taking? Is it gels?
Are you on gels? Are you on libido? When
was it taken? Are you taking short
acting injectables? If so what's your
regime? Is it into the muscle? Is it
into the subcutaneous fats? Um are you
being u and are you being fully
compliant with treatment? Have you just
taken your things leading up to the
blood test? Um, sometimes I've seen
this, uh, and this isn't slating one
medication over another, um, but
sometimes gels are fantastic at first
and then they're not and your numbers
are fine and I've got no explanation for
it. Seen it a couple of times and we're
all different and we're not machines,
although we could see it as we are, but
sometimes things just don't make sense
and it's not no real benefit in looking
for the logic there. So, I'd say like,
yeah, what are you taking? Could it be
working or not? What's your
SHBG? So, uh it could be high, it could
be low. Um so, for example, uh if your
SHBG is low, you can end up with a high
free testosterone. And a testosterone
that's too high can also make you feel
not so good as well. So, um that and I
have seen that. So, it can give you kind
of um similar symptoms paradoxically to
to before you started. So um there's
that to think about. Um then uh so
that's it. Probably best having a chat
really and also your estrogen is another
one I think is important. So estrogen or
estradile whichever you want to call it.
If that's raised that can give you nasty
side effects as well. So you can feel
emotional and if you were feeling a bit
anxious before that will look like it's
coming back. And so um your testosterone
might be too high. We can lower the dose
that would lower the estrogen and that
that can help but just bring you back
into range. your levels just might be
too high. Um, so and so there's a few
things you might need that you might
need something like an aromatase
inhibitor. I found a short course and
stopping helps. I know some doctors um
just prescribe it you straight away to
stop the side effects, but I kind of
like estrogen. I don't want you to tank
it completely. You need it for long-term
health as well.
So, I think there's so many things going
on there and it's a question I get um
like too many what if questions. Um and
you you spend too long explaining it. I
think the best thing to do is see your
physician and tell them your symptoms,
give them your blood work. And I always
ask patients to tell me what your latest
regime is, when your bloods were taken
in relation so I've got I've got all my
history there. then I can listen to you
and make a um make a kind of assumption
or something going forward. It's a
really big question to answer. So like
that's why we just want the full blood
panel um then along with your symptoms.
Sometimes patients just go here here are
my results doc and that that is
literally the email I get and it's very
hard to interpret that. Um, but the ones
who give me lots of detail, you know,
with the bloods included and everything,
it allows me to formulate quite an
accurate management plan for them.